<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Westminster, January the 30th, 1695/6 by Gregory Hascard.</title>
            <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1117</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08951687</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08951687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42080</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42080)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1286:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Westminster, January the 30th, 1695/6 by Gregory Hascard.</title>
                  <author>Hascard, Gregory.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Daniel Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Micah VII, 2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42080:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the HONOURABLE <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> AT St. <hi>MARGARET's WESTMINSTER, Jannary</hi> the 30th, 1695/6.</p>
            <p>By GREGORY HASCARD, D. D. Dean of <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Clements Danes,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Swan</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:42080:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42080:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> On <hi>January</hi> the 30th, 1695/6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>MICAH VII. 2.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>The good man is periſhed out of the earth, and there is none upright among men: they all lie in wait for blood; they bunt every man his neighbour with a net.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are the cauſe of the Prophet's ſorrow, expreſt <hi>ver.</hi> 1. ſo <hi>deep a concern</hi> it was, that the words <hi>(Wo is me)</hi> may ſignify not only mourning, but howling; which did not ariſe from a melancholy temper, or diſcontent againſt the Government, diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, peeviſhneſs, or contradiction, but from a ſerious and ſad conſideration of the ſcarcity of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42080:3"/>men truly good: So rare they were in the Land of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> as not to be found in Cluſters, in nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Families, and large Societies, but in thin and hungry Gleanings after the Vintage was over, <hi>v.</hi> 1. When the Prophet had taken an impartial view of the ſeveral Ranks and Orders in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Princes, Prieſts and People, good men, were reckon'd up; not like the muſters in St. <hi>John</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> twelve thouſand, or ſilver in the days of <hi>Solomon,</hi> but as hard to be found as the mouths of <hi>Nile,</hi> or Jewels among dirt and rubbiſh. Notwithſtanding the Law and Temple, which they profeſt and admir'd, the mighty won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that were done of old, and they believ'd, the peculiar care and tenderneſs of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Nation; faith God, <hi>I have carried them upon Eagles wings;</hi> Signal Judgments upon men of Vice, the Admonitions and Alarms of the Prophets, and other kind methods inviting to Goodneſs and true Religion, yet they were ſo degenerate and vicious, that when the Prophet came to ſearch for the fruits of Religion, and find a number of <hi>good men,</hi> he makes this ſad return, <hi>The good man is periſhed out of the earth, and there is none upright among men; they all lie in wait for blood,</hi> &amp;c. Such as paſſion as this for the want of good men, became the Prophet in all capacities, as a Man, as a Subject, and as a Prophet. As a Man,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:42080:3"/>whoſe eſſence is as much to be good and religious, as'tis to be rational; and therefore could not but be concern'd, to ſee a Nation of men ſo ſtrangely chang'd and degenerated by Vice and Luxury in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Brutes, that nothing was left of the Image of God and Manhood, beſide ſhape and laughter. As a Subject, well foreſeeing, and with grief con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, what miſery would ſuddenly betide the Nation, for want of Goodneſs and Religion. As a Prophet, that notwithſtanding the Meſſages he brought from God, and the clear Predictions he made them, what ſad Events in a ſhort time would happen to them, for want of Goodneſs and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yet they ſlighted his Errand, and were ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and reſolute in their Vices.</p>
            <p>I am afraid we have too great reaſon from the conſideration of this day, for the Prophet's Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and Exclamation. When a truly good and moſt excellent Prince fell by the bloody hands of his Rebellious Subjects, and with him our Laws and Liberties, our Apoſtolical Church, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Government, and great was the fall thereof; to the Grief of our Friends, the Joy of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the Scandal of Religion. A Murder it was of the deepeſt Die, committed upon a moſt tender Father, by Sons making high Pretences to the Spirit of God, Zeal for Chriſtianity, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, to Purity and Reformation array'd in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42080:4"/>the fineſt Dreſs and Colours, yet deeply ſtain'd by this foul Action, to the Triumph of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Laughter of the Atheiſt, the Sport of the Vicious and Lewd, but to the Sorrow of all Loyal and Good Subjects, all Honeſt and Sincere Chriſtians. To ſpend time in magnifying the Virtues and Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of our Martyr'd Sovereign, which were ſo bright, and known ſo well, outſhining the Jewels of his Crown, would be groſs Impertinency to this great Auditory; they ſpeak aloud like <hi>Abel</hi>'s blood, though their great Maſter is dead, not for Vengeance, but Imitation. I ſhall therefore only touch upon them, as they fall in with the <hi>end and intention of theſe words, The good man is periſhed out of the earth;</hi> and my following Diſcourſe upon them very ſuitable, I hope, to the Devotion of this day, which I ſhall purſue by this method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) Let us conſider wherein the goodneſs of this good man, the Prophet mentions, did expreſs it ſelf.</item>
               <item>(2.) What prevail'd or grew up in the Prophet's time, in the place of true Religion and Goodneſs.</item>
               <item>(3.) What particular Conſiderations may move us to bewail the want of true Goodneſs.</item>
            </list>
            <p>It could be wiſh'd that this dearth of Goodneſs had been only under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Religion, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar only to the Land of <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> but the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, as well as the Prophet, may juſtly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42080:4"/>bewail het barren Chriſtians, and the ſcarcity of Men truly good, notwithſtanding her Laws ſo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, ſo Divine. We all affirm indeed, That our Religion by the hand of Jeſus came from God, but our Converſation ſaith, 'tis only a new device and faſhion to wear a broad, and throw off at home. With great ſolemnity of Words and Looks we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat our Creeds; with confidence and a keen Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion we break the Commands. We pray and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with Sighs and Appearances, befitting the ſtricteſt Penitent, and the greateſt Saint; yet our Lives ſay, our Prayers are but formal Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto God, and the Table of the Lord is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. We flame with Zeal for Religion, but our practice puts out the Fire, and in the bottom of the Aſhes lie Revenge and Intereſt, Faction and a Party, which with a little breath blowing off the diſguize, appear in their natural Colours. We call our ſelves Saints and Elect, but where's the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, the Temper, and the Spirit of them? We follow Jeſus and wear his Livery, but underneath is the Paſſion of a <hi>Judas,</hi> and the fond and carnal Expectation of a <hi>Jew;</hi> and is this the Coat of thy Son <hi>Joſeph?</hi> Some there were, who murther'd their Sovereign, yet talkt loud, and diſputed warmly, and caſt themſelves into Sides and Diviſions, and all muſt be ſet at Stake for the Cauſe of God, by which they drive on their barbarous Deſign; but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42080:5"/>yet I am afraid, and could wiſh the Fear was idle, for the ſake of Chriſtianity. What was the black Charge of Pagan <hi>Corinth,</hi> may in the greateſt part be laid againſt them, <hi>who were adulterers, effeminate, thieves, covetous, revilers, extortioners,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10, 11. And I wiſh I could ſay ſuch <hi>were</hi> only ſome of them, <hi>but they are waſhed, but they are ſanctified;</hi> but the ſame Vices, or others, in ſo many ſtill do live and thrive, maintaining their old lewd Principles, as tho they endeavour'd to fulfil the Prophecy, telling us what ſhould betide Chriſtianity in the latter days, <hi>That men ſhould be lovers of themſelves, proud, boaſters, traytors, unthankful, falſe accuſers,</hi> and a ſtrange rabble of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are reckon'd up, <hi>having the form of godlineſs, but denying the power of it,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.2., 3, 4. but what availeth all that form, ſo long as <hi>Mordecai</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> lives? what ſignifies a good Religion in a bad Man's breaſt? But I am not here, beſure, to libel Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, or any of its Diſciples, who are truly Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; 'tis a great part of that Religion to be Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and cover Errors. But thus much I may venture to ſay, let our Religion be never ſo Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Apoſtolical, let it be <hi>Engliſh</hi> or <hi>Italian,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd or Popiſh, except it makes us really good, 'tis but wrangling Hypocriſy and Noiſe, not being ſerviceable to the great Deſign, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of our Souls. That we may not therefore again be deceiv'd by Names and Pretences, 'twill be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42080:5"/>prudent to conſider, wherein true Goodneſs doth conſiſt; and omitting other particulars, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon only theſe four, for which our Martyr was very Eminent, and the Authors of this Murder were ſo notoriouſly guilty of the contrary Vices.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) True Goodneſs doth expreſs it ſelf in plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſincerity in all our reſpective Dealings with Men. When the Primitive Chriſtian did ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, or treat, anſwer or determine, he did it with uprightneſs or ſimplicity, being mindful of his Maſter's command, bidding him be as gentle and harmleſs as a Dove, and allowed him the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but not the falſe and ſpeckled Skin of the Serpent to conceal his Sting and Poyſon. But the Modern Chriſtian leaving his King and Maſter's Highway of Truth and Plainneſs, and leaping common Bounds of Truth and Juſtice, by wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and turnings, and indirect Courſes, thinks to arrive at his Journeys end. Ask him counſel, he directs to your Temper and Inclination to ſcratch and pleaſe; and tells you your Houſe is ſtrong, when 'tis on Fire about your ears. If you deal and contract with him, plain Senſe is wrackt, words are perverted, and Shrugs, Looks, Silence, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and Signs, muſt all carry on his Intriegue and End; and Lying, and Hypocriſy, Equivocation, and Reſerves, and perjuryat a pinch, muſt be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to the ſame purpoſe, and you treat with an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42080:6"/>parition, one that is not what he ſeems to appear; Falſhood he calls Prudence, Treachery is good management, his own Contrivance is Diſcovery, and Trains and Schemes of Tricks and Frauds are good Foreſight and excellent Judgment; this is to lie in wait, to hunt, ſpread nets with all ſly Arts of deceit and fraud, to catch the ſimple and plain. And had its Apoſtles and early Chriſtians, either in their civil Converſation, or in their Propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Religion been inſincere and falſe, it had been confin'd to a narrower compaſs than now it is, and they whipt for Vagrants, and marke for Cheats and Impoſtors. Such are but the little Spirits, and low Souls, who wanting ſolid Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and true Prudence, which are generous and brave, fly to Tricks and Falſhood like other ſmall Animals, becauſe weak, Nature hath ſupply'd with craft. As tho God had ſo order'd all Humane Affairs, that our juſt Intereſts could not be carried on by the Rules of Honeſty, Plainneſs, and Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, except we call in Deceit and Fraud to our aſſiſtance. 'Tis only fit for a bad Cauſe to be managed by ſuitable methods, which as often miſs the deſired end as attain it, in being as eaſy to diſcover and countermine, as to contrive the Deſign, which often concludes in Scorn and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment, all not being Fools, as the man of Tricks intends they ſhould be. This Temper is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42080:6"/>moſt deſtructive to the eaſe and quiet of Humane Societies, which will always be in fits of Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Suſpicions, having heen ſo often trick'd, they are afraid they embrace a ſhadow, or anchor upon Quickſands; and whereas before they were credulous and believ'd everything, they now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing; Words have loſt their uſe, Oaths are made common Air; we know not when our buſineſs is at an end; Niceties are infinite, there are ſtill ſome ſly Quirks, Fetches, and Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons behind, which melt the Glew and Cement of Converſation, and the ſacred Bonds of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Frauds and Flatteries ſpring from fear and a ſervile temper, and many times end ingloriouſly. The Punick Faith is more a Brand, then Valour, the Renown of that Ancient Nation. And poor <hi>Regulus</hi>'s Honeſty carries more Fame with it than <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Conſulſhip. And many times the Doom of an <hi>Achitophel,</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> that Fox, and other Men of tricks, hath been very ſevere. Like <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8th, who came in like a Fox, rul'd like a Lyon, and dy'd like a Dog. Yet, notwhichſtanding all this, fince our martyr is periſhed, may we not juſtly complain, it becoming this mournful Day, that Faith and Truth are departed from Men? May we not ſuſpect when our great Maſter comes again, whether, in this ſenſe, he will find Faith and Uprightneſs on Earth? I with King <hi>David</hi>'s
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42080:7"/>times be not our own, if they be, I am ſure we ought to uſe his Prayer, Pſal. 12. 1, 2. <hi>Help, Lord, for the good man ceaſeth; and the faithful fail from among the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Goodneſs expreſſeth it ſelf in the exerciſe of good Nature, and Charitable Allowances for the Errors of other. Such is the State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Chriſtian World, that her publick So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eieties and private Perſons, her Saints in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree as well as common Mortals, may be guilty ſometimes of a wilful Offence, often of Frailties, Errors, Surprizes, and Miſcarriages. The good Man, like his gentle Maſter, knowing the ſad Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Humane Life, our Mold, Frame, and Company, ſometimes conceals, always judges candidly, interprets fairly, and by ſoft and eaſy Methods endeavours a cure. The Man of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, of greater Vices, and more ill Nature, ſpreads and inflames, wreſts and aggravates, and pours in Vinegar inſtead of Oyl to make the Wound eaſily curable, deſperate and mortal, and advances himſelf upon the dead Body. Such Men do not heartily mourn for the want of Virtue and Religion, but are in wardly pleaſed that there are miſtakes and errors in the World, which afford them the pleaſure of Murmuring and Complaining; and like <hi>Belzebub,</hi> that Prince of Flies, delight in, and feaſts upon Wounds and Sores; and are made ſerviceable to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42080:7"/>their Hypocriſy, and Steps to their Intereſt and Ambition. Diſorders and Abuſes which might have been redreſt by gentle Treatments and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Proſecuitions, turn into Confuſion and Ruin by utmoſt Rigors and Severities; which makes Men deſperate, and that makes them formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſometimes prevailing; as tho Juſtice and Peace, Laws and Liberties, might not be ſecur'd but by Extremity and Cruelty. The good Man knows how to reform, but not to extirpate, to pardon Crimes that are paſt, yet to prevent them in time to come; who is juſt in the uſe of Law and Right, but not ſevere and vexatious, and like that God above, who by Mercy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieves preſerves the Reputation of his Juſtice, and governs the ſturdy World as well as by utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and Executions. And when Men are ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Juſt in Holy Writ, as <hi>Neah,</hi> and <hi>Foſeph, Corna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> and Chriſt himſelf; their Juſtice did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſ only in doing no wrong, and in keeping cloſe to the Law, but in Abatement and Remiſſion of Ringts and Liberties, in Goodneſs, Charity, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and Humanity. And as they were ready to cover and pardon faults, ſo never quick and paſſionate to upbraid; and therefore we never read when the miſunderſtanding was between the two Saints, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that the one reminded the other of his former Rerſecution of the Church,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42080:8"/>or St. <hi>Paul</hi> upbraided St. <hi>Peter</hi> of his denying of his Maſter; or either of them <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> with her former Unchaſtity; 'twas ſufficient to them their Repentance was ſincere. But the Authors of this Bloody Day would give no allowance for the few and ſmall Errors in their Prince, in the hard Circimſtances of his Life and Goverment, but like that accurſed <hi>Cain,</hi> took pleaſure to diſcover the Nakedneſs of a moſt tender Father of his Country, yet granted large Patents to themſelve to Sin ſecurely by, and made his Conceſſions for Peace ſake, COnfeſſions of his Miſtakes, and thoſe they made unpardonable. Men that prerend moſt to Perſection and Infallibility, are many times guilty of as groſs Miſtakes and Follies as others, and evermore ill-natur'd, as great a fault as any. The good Man makes the beſt Ruler, Subject, Neighbour, and Friend, and hath moſt of the Spirit of God, and the Temper of Jeſus in him. And if all the World was wanting of this Goodneſs, the Earth would be but Confuſion and a Slaughter-houſe. Such are the Errours of all Mankind, neceſſarily calling for Favour and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; yet notwithſtanding the eaſe of Mankind depends on this good Temper, and 'tis a principal Branch of our Religion: The concern of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet may be juſtly our own, <hi>That the righteous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42080:8"/>are taken away;</hi> 'twas then a Calamity, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 57.1. and the Language of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> may fit the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, <hi>There is none that doeth good, no, not one;</hi> but adding to the heap of common Sins, and then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming againſt them.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The good Man is of a Spirit truly publick, whoſe happineſs is not only to hug himſelf, and to be well at home; but his Care and Affection looks abroad; and his King and Country, his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latives and Neighbours, are his common concern, who being plac'd in thoſe Communities and Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, like a compaſſionate Member, is ſick when the Head doth ache; is expoſed to danger, when it is unſecure; who mourns and is poor; who is weak and caſt down, when his common Parent or Fellow-being is diſtreſt and languiſheth; who is diligent and active to preſerve the Fame to allay the Fears, to prevent the Dangers of a Kingdom, to reconcile Diviſions and Parties in it, making its Greatneſs and Safety his own: <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Fortunes embark'd together in one common Bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom. This is not only the good Man's Intereſt and Safety, and therefore is as prudent as he is good, but 'tis his Fame and Reputation to be brave and generous, for this gave the Characters of Renown and Greatneſs to the Men of Ancient Times, who eaſily ſacrificed their Pleaſures and Fortunes when they came in Conpetition with the Publick
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42080:9"/>Good; who had none of thoſe ſtingy and mean Principles, to turn Church and State into a Flame to warm their Hands, or gratify Revenge; who had none of thoſe low and little Spirits, only to weather the Storm for their own Lives, and that Peace might be only in their days, tho their eaſe and ſoftneſs (like great Calms portending Storms and Thunder) brought heavier Calamities upon Poſterity, and the Entail was not to be cut off. They did not think the Word, and all its good things were created ſolely upon their a account, and were to centre in their little ſelves, or that they and the World were to dye together. Let the Wind blow, and let the Ship of Government ſtrike upon a Rock, yet they have provided a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Plank to ſwim to Shore. <hi>Eſther</hi>'s Beauty will keep her ſafe in <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi>'s Court, and ſhe need not put her ſelf upon that hazard for the ſake of her Nation, if <hi>I periſh, I periſh;</hi> nor idlely wiſh ſhe had been born in ſome other Age, when ſhe could have been more ſecurely kind unto her Country; but probably thought ſhe was born for ſuch a time as this. And <hi>Daniel</hi> might have thought that his Gift of unfolding Dreams and Viſions, might have made him great and ſafe, and he need not run the venture for his Religion, of the Lyon's Den. Theſe men ſcorn'd Eaſe and Danger, Intereſt and Pleaſure, to ſerve their Generation, and King, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42080:9"/>Country, Laws and Religion, withoutmaking them terms of Diviſion and Peeviſhneſs, were Father and Mother, Siſter and Brother, and their dear Selves too. Theſe things indeed are written for our Example, upon whom the ends of the World are come; but alas, the Apoſtle tells us, Men ſhould <hi>then be levers of themſelves.</hi> There are not now ſo many <hi>Jehu</hi>'s left, <hi>Come, ſee my zeal for the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> except we call Pride and Ambition two mighty Virtues. And where is the <hi>Lot</hi> now, that is vext with the unclean Converſation of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> is long ſince dead, and few eyes like his <hi>guſh out with tears, becauſe men keep not his Laws.</hi> Diſobedience to them, and Vice, being counted only natural Freedoms and lawful Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Poor <hi>Uriah</hi> is ſlain, and will not riſe again in this Age; the Ark, and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> abide in Tents, and ſhall I go down to my Houſe to eat and drink? And 'tis the Scandal of Religion, that having ſo good a Maſter, who went about doing good, and made the benefit of Mankind, who ſo little deſerv'd it, his proper Buſineſs; that there ſhould be ſo many Workers of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty found among his Diſciples. Had this narrow Principle govern'd our Martyr, he had reign'd longer, and gone later to Heaven; or had it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd in our Forefathers, who planted and toil'd for their Poſterity, Hoſpitals and Publick Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42080:10"/> Arts and uſeful Employment, had been as rare as good Men; and the preſent Age would have had leſs Plenty and more Labour, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd like the <hi>Oſtrich</hi>'s Egg; and inſtead of Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Monuments erected to them, they would have had Anger and Reproach, and all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſhould have call'd them Evil.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) The good Man takes up Religion only to ſerve a ſpiritual Purpoſe. He looks into the other World, and firmly concludes, doubtleſs there is a God, doubtleſt there is a Reward for the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous; he reflects upon himſelf in this, and finds, he is not yet fitted and pre-qualify'd for that Divine State; he therefore enters into Religion to ſerve theſe two mighty ends; every day to confirm his Faith about the Being of God, the Immortality of the Soul, the day of Account and Retribution, to believe whatever Chriſt hath promis'd or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover'd; and certainly thinks theſe things in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are very true. This Perſuaſion makes him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon, and reſign to God; quiets his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, expels his Fears, ſupports his Hopes, makes him more humble and charitable, juſt and true; keeps him in a continual Senſe and Reverence of God, and in univerſal Love with all Mankind. This is truly a good Man, whoſe Religion is pure and undefil'd, and carries a reſpect only to another World. All other Religion without this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42080:10"/>good Purpoſe, is only Faſhion or Faction, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy and Formality, Superſtition or Intereſt, whereby he honours and ſerves only himſelf, but diſgraces his God. Such Men have made Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, this or that, ſo various, that you may as well define the thing that Men call Wit, as what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion means. Sometimes 'tis Temper, change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by Weather and Company; ſometimes 'tis Diſcontent ariſing from Diſappointment of one Party, and now the Man is reſolv'd to ſtrike in with another; ſometimes 'tis Deſign; and Creed, Sacraments, and Prayers, are good Engins and Trains to gain it. As tho the Son of God came with all the greatneſs of his Miracles, and ſuffer'd all thoſe Sorrows and Indignities upon Earth, only to ſet up a new Model of Government, to erect ſome new Schemes of Trade; and the great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention ſhould be, whether the Monopoly of it ſhould be at <hi>Rome;</hi> or elſewhere; and in the modern Phraſe, a rich and a thriving Man ſhould be call'd a good Man. For Religion without real Goodneſs, is Scene and Pageantry, Noiſe and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and any thing but what it pretends to be. Without plain Obedience to the Laws of God and Reformation of Manners, Religion is but Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and Bribes for Divine Juſtice. To ſeem to be Religious, and not to bridle our Tongues; to pretend to Faith, and ſhew no good Works;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42080:11"/>to boaſt of the Spirit of Chriſt, without his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, the Love of God, without Duty and Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and to be a Chriſtian, and yet without Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is a Contradiction, and in effect is to be called Good without Goodneſs, or Chriſtians without Chriſtianity. For if you look to the Laws and Deſign of Chriſt, his Example and Miracles in Confirmation of it, the whole Conſtitution and Frame of his Religion, you will find it only this, to make Men better here, and to ſave them hereafter, and ſo eſſential to Chriſtianity, that you may as ſoon call a Man, a Man, without Spirit or Soul; or the Hypocrites Trumpet, a Victory, as men Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious without Honeſty and Goodneſs; and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Sacraments, Temples and Altars, and all the Externals of Religion, Miniſter unto that great Deſign; and the diſcovery of Chriſt, call'd our Creeds, are not to tell us fine Notions and Curioſities about God and that other State, but to influence our Lives, and give us good Hopes of Heaven. Here our Religion Centers, and this alone will do us good. To hear Men talk loudly, and diſpute angerly about Religion, and yet want Goodneſs, is equal to the folly of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling about the Poſſeſſions of the Moon; they worſhip, and are warm about they know not what; ſomething that will not belong to them; to fight for that which they intend never to uſe,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42080:11"/>that is to ſay, to correct their Follies and Lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; 'tis to expoſe their Quiet and Lives ſor Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles, and the unknown Land. And without this great end, Men may as well lay aſide the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it, and give themſelves, and the World leſs Trouble, and there would be leſs Cenſures and Rigors in the World. For let us deal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially with our ſelves, and others, Who were the Cauſes of this Bloody Fact, and yet moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly charg'd Popery upon our Martyr; Whoſe is the beſt Religion? his, who fetcheth a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for his Vice from <hi>Rome:</hi> Or his, who gives himſelf a Licenſe to Sin? His, who condemns the Half Communion? Or he that never receives at all, except it be for an Office or a Vote. His, who believes the Pains of Purgatory? Or his, who laughs at that Doctrine, yet lives as tho there was neither Purgatory nor Hell, but paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Fires in both. The Conſiſtory is not more Holy than the Conclave, if the ſame Vices be in both; there is little difference between him that ſhall take away one of the commands, and him that ſhall conſtantly break another. The Doctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> naturally lead to Vice, the worſt Religion in the Chriſtian World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do ſo; and the Conſtitution of our own directly leads to Virtue, one of the beſt Notes to know the beſt Church by. Yet if our Lives be
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42080:12"/>equally wicked, 'tis no great matter who is in the pureſt Church. 'Tis fit that the beſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church in the whole World, ſuch is this of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſhould have the beſt Men in it; and all its Members may be ſo if they pleaſe, and ſeek for no other, but gracing it with works of Goodneſs and Diſcipline, are themſelves an honeſt and upright Converſation. This is the good Man we want ſo much, this is the <hi>Iſraelite</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, in whom is no guile. This is a true Diſciple of Chriſt, and ſuch that are ſo minded, there will be Peace upon them, and the whole <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) What grew up and prevail'd in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet's time, in the place of true Religion or Goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Superſtition and falſe Religion, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally produces trouble and diſquiet in all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments. Worthy Conceptions of God and Chriſt, and Obedience to his plain Laws, are ſo far from claſhing with Authority, that they give it greater ſtrength and value; Obedience in ſuch a Religion being a mighty Duty. But Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which entertains ſuch courſe Notions of God, making him Falſe and Cruel, Peeviſh and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourſome, Sowre and Uncertain; makes its Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the ſame Temper, thinking it excellent Religion to imitate ſuch a God, which muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42080:12"/>diſturb Societies, and be troubleſome to all Mankind. What ſtrange Subjects, Neigbours, and Friends muſt thoſe be, who are always ſullen and melancholy, fearful and diſcontented; theſe cannot but weaken and allay the pleaſure and ſafety of Neighbourhoods and Communities? Let us draw the black Catalogue of all the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties and Butcheries, Confuſions and Ruins, that have betided the World, and you ſhall find moſt of them owing their Original to Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of falſe Religion; it being the nature of theſe two, to call Humour and Fleſh, Intereſt or Faſhion, Deſign or Education, Cloudy-days and Ambition, and the like, the working of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the Church of God, Decrees of Heaven, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, Fundamentals of Religion, and Conditions of Salvation. And if they fancy theſe to be oppos'd and totter, Violence and Fraud, Blood and Diſorder, muſt all club together for their Support and Reputation. Superſtition and blind Zeal, like <hi>AEneas</hi> with his Father and his falſe gods upon his Back; and <hi>Sampſon</hi> with his Eyes put out, will paſs through Flames, and pull the Government about their Ears, and make a Common Grave for themſelves and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. And all the dear Relations of Prince and Subjects, Friends and Allies, (which tye Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind together) have been ſnapt in ſunder, when
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42080:13"/>Superſtition hath been in its raving fits and freaks; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Valley of <hi>Hinnom,</hi> the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Maſſacres, and this mournful Day. The Prophet had reaſon to cry out, <hi>Wo is me,</hi> when he ſaw Religion dwindle into Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and no real Goodneſs left. He could not but fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee how this would affect the civil Part of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and when the Temple was made a den of Thieves inſtead of <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, there would be violence and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining in the Street; ſo neceſſary a Connexion there is between Peace and true Religion, and Diſorders and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. For when once true Religion is hair'd and frighted out of its Wits, it grows giddy and foams, is quarrelſome and clamorous, and calls every thing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, but what really is ſo, Faith upon God, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Charity. Theſe two Eſſential Parts, the Soul and Body of Religion, make Men meek and peaceable, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd and obliging, which are fruits of the Spirit, and the great Pleaſure and Security of Kingdoms and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. And whereas Chriſtianity is firſt pure, and then peaceable; Superſtition, which wears its Colours, is earthly and vexatious, made up of whimſy and vapour, is contentious and fierce, implacable and revengeful, enough to make the compaſſionate Prophet uſe this Excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when true Goodneſs was gone out of the World, and only Superſtition left, <hi>Wo is me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Wicked Lives in the Profeſſors of the true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which will certainly cauſe Miſery and Ruin in a Nation, which ſo comes to paſs, not only by Divine De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees paſſing Sentence upon a wicked and profligate People, but from the natural tendency of Vice, which is as much the direct Cauſe of Miſery, as Poyſon is of Death. We curiouſly inquire and ask the queſtion, why the Strength and Reputation, the Riches and Courage of a Nation are gone? And we aſcribe it either to the hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, determining the Fates and Periods of Kingdoms,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42080:13"/>the Influences of the Heavens, or ſuch more ſecret Cauſes; or we anſwer as our preſent Fancy, Peeviſhneſs, or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction do ſuggeſt; but forget the nature of Vice and Wickedneſ, which do as fatally deſtroy, as the Devil and the Stars, the Sword and Enemy, and in Conjunction. Secret Fires and a raging Peſtilence, the Blaſts of Heaven, and unexpected Defeats, are many times ſent by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Hand of Providence, by the juſt Provocation of our Follies; yet as ill Effects as they, are conceiv'd in the natural Womb of Vice. The genuine Iſſue of Pride and Luſt, Ambition and Revenge, Idleneſs and Injuſtice, and other Vices, are ſo deform'd and monſtrous, that they would create an horror to deſcribe and view them. From whence come Wars, but from your. Luſts? St. <hi>James</hi> doth hint to us to ask the queſtions a little further, From whence generally come Poverty and Contempt, weak Bodies and weaker Heads, Diviſions and Treacheries, Cowardiſe and Meanneſs, and other ſad effects, but from the Spawn of Vice, it robbing Subjects of that juſt Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Qualification, which alone make a Kingdom to flouriſh. And if we look back upon the Calamities of all Ages paſt, the Miſeries and Troubles that now vex the preſent, you will find the chief Spring and Original, to be prophane and vicious Living. Real Goodneſs and Religion being Prudence and true Policy, Strength and Courage, and every thing that gives Luſtre and Security to a Nation And when the Wiſe and Ingenious have drawn their Schemes and Projects for advance of Trade and Power, the Honour and Intereſt of a Nation, they always ſuppos'd Virtue and Religion to be the firſt ſtep; otherwiſe they began at the wrong end. And what can we expect from the Juſtice of God, (if we be real Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, as we pretend to be) but that if we prophane his Temple, he will blaſt our Vineyards. And it hath been look'd upon by all wiſe and good Men, as ſure a ſign,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42080:14"/>as a Voice in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Temple, <hi>Let us be gone;</hi> and more certain than a blazing Comet, or a monſtrous Birth, that the ruins of Kingdoms and Families then drew on, when Religion by ill living was contemn'd, and no real Goodneſs left. And therefore when the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian deſcribes the Cauſes of the Deſtruction of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Britains,</hi> he tells us, They were Proud and Luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, haters of a plain Truth, and lovers of an handſome Lye, and indifferently concern'd for what pleaſed or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed God; and then concludes, <hi>Non igitur mirandum eſt tales degeneres parriam ſuam à mittere quam predicto modo maculabant.</hi> 'Tis no wonder that ſuch degenerate <hi>Britains,</hi> who nothing of their brave Anceſtors in them, but their Name, ſhould loſe that Country which they defil'd in ſuch a manner, and now ſpued them out. Our Prophet therefore ſeeing Vice to thrive, and grow faſhio able; and ſome Sins to be eſteemed good Breeding and Education, 'tis no wonder he cries out, <hi>Wo is me,</hi> as tho from his Tower he ſaw Armies and the Plague, Wild Beaſts and Inundations to invade and deſtroy the Land. So diſmal are the fruits of Vice, or want of real Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>(<hi>Laſtly,</hi>) Atheiſtical Perſuaſions prevail'd, or there was no Religion at all. As Vice naturally leads ot Atheiſm, and Superſtition often concludes in it, ſo Atheiſm is very kind to Vice again, and often ends in Superſtition; ſuch dear Relations are theſe three to one another; and ſuch a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle do men make when once they are giddy, and out of the way of this ſubſtantial Religion. And what greater Calamity can betide Mankind than a contempt of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and that folly, to imagine that there is not a Being we call a God; but that all things tumble up and down in great uncertainty and darkneſs; and the thing we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is only a Creature of Fear and Cuſtom, Policy or Fiction: Government and Friendſhip, Relations and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42080:14"/>Truſt, and other great things which make Mankind hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, have loſt their vital Spirits, becauſe Reverence of a God, checks of Conſcience, and the hopes and fears of Rewards and Puniſhments in the other World are gone. And publick Laws are too ſcanty to recompence the loſs of real Goodneſs and Religion; and Fame and Honour to keep Men in due Bounds, will prove but airy things, when reſpect to God and Virtue is laid aſide. The Man of Revenge may aſſaſſinate his Neighbour, if it can be but a work of darkneſs, with ſecurity; and may defraud and cozen, if by Privacy and Art he can keep his Fame and Reputation; he fears no Puniſhment in the other World for all this Villany, and 'tis his ſafe Intereſt and Pleaſure in this. 'Tis the Imperfection of Humane So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties in making Laws not to be able to reach many private Sins, and ſuch is the skill of men to baffle the plaineſt Laws; if there was not the dread of an higher Hand, Laws would loſe their Edge, and Mankind would be in a ſtate of War. For tho the force of Religion doth not prevail upon every Man, yet it doth upon many; upon moſt in ſome degree, and is apt and fit to gain upon all. And therefore Men of Contrivance and Policy, if themſelves had no real Perſuaſion of Religion, yet ever thought it neceſſary to infuſe the belief of it into thoſe they had to manage; ſuppoſing that all other Methods to rule the World, were only Formalities and Entreaties. And tis plain, what they acted upon the account of State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, is really ſo. A Land without Religion, is a World without a Sun, producing Horror and Confuſion, and the Prophets Wo. And the belief of a God Without real Goodneſs, is to ſay, there is no God at all.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) What particular Reaſons may move us to bewail the want of real Goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) The want of it is the principal Cauſe of our Diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions about Religion. Men of Wiſdom and Sobriety
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42080:15"/>cannot but be pleas'd to have the methods of Salvation plain, and the Characters eaſy, whereby they may judge, whether they ſhall be ſaved or no; but it ſometimes happens that good Men live and walk, where different ways are chalk'd out, and ſeveral Voices are heard to ſay, <hi>Lo here, and lo there lies the road to Jeruſalem;</hi> their Opinions are numerous, their Arguings warm, their Cenſures ſevere, every one pretending Heaven and true Religion is only with them. How muſt the good Man carry himſelf here, when his Birth, Privacy, Imployment, and other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Life will not permit him to conſider and conclude, who hath the greateſt truth on his ſide. The only Gound among theſe Quickſands, Waves, and Winds, variety of Opinions as ill as they, to anchor on, is real Goodneſs, This being the beſt evidence that our Faith is true, our Spirit Divine, Decrers irreverſible, the great preparative to Heaven, to which all other parts in Religion do miniſter, in which moſt Perſuaſions (tho ſometimes they miſtake the means to it) do agree, moſt ſuitable to natural Reaſon; the deſign of Chriſt's coming, and the ſolemn end of all Religion. If this good Man miſtakes, yet ſo long as his Error toucheth not upon the great Article of Faith, nor Goodneſs, he hath a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful High-Prieſt at God's right hand, who will accept his Sacrifice, and pardon the blemiſh of it. He is ſafe and ſecure, and is a <hi>Iſraclite</hi> indeed, tho he hath not the Phylacteries and Fringes of a nicer Rabbi; tho he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call over all the Points of the Compaſs, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all the Sailer's terms, yet he is in the Channel to <hi>Sion,</hi> not having made Shipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience. And tho this Church of <hi>England,</hi> which our Martyr ſo heartily defended with his Pen and his Blood, be charg'd by ſome with Hereſy, and others with Superſtition and Secular Intereſt, yet being ſure that her Faith is Primitive, her Diſcipline, Ceremonies, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42080:15"/>Homilles, and whole Conſtitution, are model'd for, and directly lead to a good Converſation, we may fix in her, and not grow giddy by turning round in all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions. Nothing giving more ſatisfaction to the Mind in a divided Age, that we ſhall not miſcarry in our hopes of Heaven, that when our purpoſes in Religion are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, to make us better Men than the common Lump and Maſs of Mankind; that we are now deſigning only to be good, and to have our Converſation as becomes the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">(2) Real Goodneſs is the beſt way to unite us among our ſelves. Religion upon any other account than the hopes of Heaven above, and real Goodneſs below, is changeable; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only Faſhion, Intereſt, or Humour, which will dwindle into as many Diviſions as there are in the World. Religion that aims not at Goodneſs, is nice and clamorous, worldly and uncertain, which naturally produce Factions and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions. Religion or Wiſdom from above is gentle and eaſy to be entreated, plain and ſubſtantial, which eaſily beget Unity and Charity, great parts of Chriſtianity, and as great Bleſſings of Mankind. Real Goodneſs pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges our Judgment, removes our Prejudices; then we eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcern what is Notion, and Opinion, and Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and what is ſolid and practical Truth; what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and what is plain, what may be parred with for peace-ſake, and what is to be retain'd; what is Soul and and Heaven, and what is Fleſh and Blood. The great occaſion of Differences that have vext the Chriſtian World, and been its Scandal, hath ſprung from the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and Peeviſhneſs, idle Diſputes, Conteſts of Power and Gain. For tho muſt in their religious Heats pretend Faith and Goodneſs, and entitle other things with thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Na<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, yet they confute themſelves in the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, being guily of Cruelty, Hypocriſy, and falſhood, things directly contrary to the Chriſtian faith.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42080:16"/>They kill Jeſus, to ſave Chriſt; diſgrace Religion, in ſo maintaining of it. And would Men be in earneſt in this pretence, the great Contentions would draw to an end. For let us but leave things controverted and dark to the Schools; for Diſcipline, Order, and things of indifferency ſubmit to the Wiſdom of our Governors; and let not Factories and Changes mix with our Churches, and call Intereſt Chriſtianity, and ſtrip our ſelves of Paſſion and hopes of Victory; there would be only left Faith and a good Life, neceſſary to Salvation; ſuch as Chriſt and his Apoſtles taught, the Primitive Chriſtians practiſed, and were ſaved by, plain and manifeſt to all. And then the only Contention would be Honeſt and truly Chriſtian, who ſhould be the beſt Men; and ſome mens Zeal would therefore cool, the flaming Bigot not always having this good deſign, to receive the Kingdom of God as a little Child, in ſimplicity and goodneſs to grow thereby. It being eaſy to obſerve, that an Age full of Contention about Religion was not always the beſt; and when the Church, as in the firſt Three hundred years was truly good, it had moſt Unity within its Pale. Vice directly ſtirring up Wars and Feuds, and Virtue Peace and Love; and to reform mens Lives, is the beſt method to bring them into truth; and <hi>if our Converſation be in Heaven,</hi> we ſhall be exerciſing and ſinging <hi>Peace of Earth,</hi> Duty to our King, <hi>Good will to all men;</hi> the ſhort and eaſy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to bring us to the place where the Sould of our Bleſſed Martyr dwells, that with him, <hi>and the Spirits of Juſt Men made perfect, we may ſing Praiſes and Hallelujahs to the Lamb, and him that ſits upon the Throne, bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>A Sermon preach'd before the King, at His Majeſty's Chappel in <hi>Windſo-Caſtle, November</hi> 10. 1695. By <hi>Gregory Haſcard,</hi> D. D. Dean of <hi>Windſor,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty. Publiſhed by his Majeſty's Speci<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Command Printed for <hi>Daniel Brown,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Swan</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42080:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
